<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-jones-tsvwg-transport-for-satellite-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Transport for Satellite">Enhancing Transport Protocols over
    Satellite Networks</title>

    <author fullname="Tom Jones" initials="T" surname="Jones">
      <organization>University of Aberdeen</organization>

      <address>
        <email>tom@erg.abdn.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Godred Fairhurst" initials="G" surname="Fairhurst">
      <organization>University of Aberdeen</organization>

      <address>
        <email>gorry@erg.abdn.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Nicolas Kuhn" initials="N" surname="Kuhn">
      <organization>CNES</organization>

      <address>
        <email>nicolas.kuhn@cnes.fr</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Border" initials="J" surname="Border">
      <organization>Hughes Network Systems, LLC</organization>

      <address>
        <email>border@hns.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Emile Stephan" initials="E" surname="Stephan">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <email>emile.stephan@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2021" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Transport</area>

    <!--<workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup> -->

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>QUIC, SATCOM, Transport</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>IETF transport protocols such as TCP, SCTP and QUIC are designed to
      function correctly over any network path. This includes networks paths
      that utilise a satellite link or network. While transport protocols
      function, the characteristics of satellite networks can impact
      performance when using the defaults in standard mechanisms, due to the
      specific characteristics of these paths.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC2488"></xref> and <xref target="RFC3135"></xref>
      describe mechanisms that enable TCP to more effectively utilize the
      available capacity of a network path that includes a satellite system.
      Since publication, both application and transport layers and satellite
      systems have evolved. Indeed, the development of encrypted protocols
      such as QUIC challenges currently deployed solutions, for satellite
      systems the capacity has increased and commercial systems are now
      available that use a range of satellite orbital positions.</t>

      <t>This document follows the terminology proposed in <xref target="I-D.irtf-panrg-path-properties"></xref> to describe the current characterises of common satellite
      paths. This document also describes considerations when implementing and deploying
      reliable transport protocols that are intended to work efficiently over
      paths that include a satellite system. It discusses available network
      mitigations and offers advice to designers of protocols and operators of
      satellite networks.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="s-introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>Satellite communications (SATCOM) systems have long been used to
      support point-to-point links and specialised networks. The predominate
      current use today is to support Internet Protocols. Typical example
      applications include: use as an access technology for remote locations,
      backup and rapid deployment of new services, transit networks, backhaul
      of various types of IP networks, and provision to mobile environments
      (maritime, aircraft, etc.).</t>

      <t>In most scenarios, the satellite IP network segment forms only
      one part of the end-to-end path used by an Internet transport protocol.
      This means that user traffic can experience a path that includes a
      satellite network combined with a wide variety of other network
      technologies (Ethernet, cable modems, WiFi, cellular, radio links, etc).
      Although a user can sometimes know the presence of a satellite service,
      a typical user does not deploy special software or applications when a
      satellite network is being used. Users are often unaware of the
      technologies underpinning the links forming a network path.</t>

      <t>Satellite path characteristics have an effect on the operation of
      transport protocols, such as TCP, SCTP or QUIC. Transport Protocol
      performance can be affected by the magnitude and variability of the
      network delay. When transport protocols perform poorly the link
      utilization can be low. Techniques and recommendations have been made
      that can improve the performance of transport protocols when the path
      includes as satellite network.</t>

      <t>The end-to-end performance of an application using an Internet path
      can be impacted by the path characteristics, such as the Bandwidth-Delay
      Product (BDP) of the links and network devices forming the path. It can
      also be impacted by underlying mechanisms used to manage the radio
      resources. </t>

      <t>Performance can be impacted at several layers. For instance, the page
      load time for a complex page can be much larger when a path includes a
      satellite system. A significant contribution to the reduced performance
      arises from the initialisation and design of transport mechanisms. </t>

      <t>Although mechanisms are designed for use across Internet paths, not
      all designs are performant when used over the wide diversity of path
      characteristics that can occur. This document therefore considers the
      implications of Internet paths that include a satellite system. The
      analysis and conclusions might also apply to other network systems that
      also result in characteristics that differ from typical Internet
      paths.</t>

      <t>RFC2488 specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet
      Community, relating to use of the standards-track Transmission Control
      Protocol (TCP) mechanisms over satellite channels <xref
      target="RFC2488"></xref>. A separate RFC,<xref target="RFC2760"></xref>,
      identified research issues and proposed mitigations for satellite
      paths.</t>

      <t>Since the publication of these RFCs many TCP mechanisms have become
      widely used. In particular, this includes a series of mitigation based on
      Performance Enhancing Proxies (PEPs) <xref target="RFC3135"></xref> that
      split the protocol at the transport layer. Although PEPs are now a common
      component of satellite systems, their use slows the deployment of new
      transport protocols and mechanisms (each of which demands an update to
      the PEP functionality). This has made it difficult for new protocol
      extensions to achieve comparable performance over satellite channels. In
      addition, protocols with strong requirements on authentication and
      privacy such as QUIC <xref target="RFC9000"></xref>
      are not able to be split using a PEP and mitigation, and need to
      therefore use other methods.</t>

      <t>XXX Note from the current authors: This document currently focuses on
      Geosynchronous Earth Orbit (GEO) satellite systems, the authors solicit
      feedback and experience from users and operators of satellite systems
      using other orbits. XXX</t>

<!--
      <t>The remainder of this document is divided as follows:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t><xref target="s-systems"></xref> identifies common
          characteristics of a SATCOM network that can impact the operation of
          the transport protocols. This complements the description of <xref
          target="RFC2488"></xref>.</t>

          <t><xref target="s-characteristics"></xref> discusses specific
          characteristics that need to be considered when implementing and
          deploying transport protocols and highlights key changes since the
          publication of <xref target="RFC2488"></xref>.</t>

          <t><xref target="s-below-transport"></xref> outlines existing
          deployed mitigations that operate below the transport protocol
          layer. This offers advice to designers and operators of satellite
          networks.</t>

          <t><xref target="s-transport"></xref> outlines transport protocol
          mechanisms defined that may benefit with satellite networks specific
          tuning and optimization. In particular it discusses on end-to-end
          considerations, and the mechanisms that impact performance of
          encrypted transports.</t>
  
          <t>Finally, <xref target="s-proto-spec"></xref> provides a summary of the features recommended
          for modern transport protocols.</t>
	</list></t>
-->
    </section>

    <section anchor="pan-terminology" title="SATCOM terminology">

	    <t>This section follows the terminology proposed in <xref target="I-D.irtf-panrg-path-properties"></xref> to describe a generic SATCOM system for broadband access. This description is inline with the one proposed in <xref target="RFC8975"></xref>.</t> 
	<t>A generic SATCOM system could contain the following entities: <list style="symbols"> 
		<t>A: A Host providing the end service (e.g. web server);</t>
		<t>B: A Node being the point-of-presence for the SATCOM system;</t>
		<t>C: A Node gathering network functions (e.g. firewall, PEP, caching services, etc.);</t>
		<t>D: A Node gathering MAC and PHY functionnalities (a.k.a. the satellite gateway);</t>
		<t>E: A Node being one of the satellite (if there are several satellites) (this node could include network layer functions);</t>
		<t>F: A Node receiving the signal from the satellite (a.k.a. the satellite terminal);</t>
		<t>G: A Host providing the end service (e.g. web browser).</t>
	    </list></t>
	    <t>These entities would be interconnected with path elements which properties differ from one SATCOM system to another. <xref target="I-D.irtf-panrg-path-properties"></xref> provides properties that can be discussed to describe the path. These properties are exploited throughout the whole document to describe SATCOM systems.</t>
	    <t>While the paths interconnecting the entities (1) A to B, (2) B to C, (3) C to D and (4) F to G are quite generic for all the systems, and not specific for SATCOM systems, some properties need to be discussed:<list style="symbols">
		<t>Protocol Features available</t>
		<t>Transport Protocols available</t>
		<t>Transparency</t>
	    </list></t>
	    <t>The paths (1) D to E and (2) D to F are quite specific to SATCOM systems. In particular, the following elements, provided by <xref target="I-D.irtf-panrg-path-properties"></xref>, are in the scope of this document and deserve some description: <list style="symbols">
		    <t>Symmetric Path</t>
		    <t>Disjointness</t>
		    <t>Transparency</t>
		    <t>Link Capacity</t>
		    <t>Link Usage</t>
		    <t>One-Way Delay</t>
		    <t>One-Way Delay Variation</t>
		    <t>One-Way Packet Loss</t>
	    </list></t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="s-systems" title="Satellite Systems">
      <t>Satellite communications systems have been deployed using many space
      orbits, including low earth orbit, medium earth orbits, geosynchronous
      orbits, elliptical orbits and more. This document considers the
      characteristics of all satellite networks.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Many communications satellites are located at Geostationary Orbit
          (GEO) with an altitude of approximately 36,000 km <xref
          target="Sta94"></xref>. At this altitude the orbit period is the
          same as the Earth's rotation period. Therefore, each ground station
          is always able to "see" the orbiting satellite at the same position
          in the sky. The propagation time for a radio signal to travel twice
          that distance (corresponding to a ground station directly below the
          satellite) is 239.6 milliseconds (ms) <xref target="Mar78"></xref>.
          For ground stations at the edge of the view area of the satellite,
          the distance traveled is 2 x 41,756 km for a total propagation delay
          of 279.0 ms <xref target="Mar78"></xref>. These delays are for one
          ground station-to-satellite-to-ground station route (or "hop").
          Therefore, the propagation delay for a packet and the corresponding
          reply (one round-trip time or RTT) could be at least 558 ms. The RTT
          is not based solely due to satellite propagation time and will be
          increased by other factors, such as the serialisation time,
          including any FEC encoding/ARQ delay and propagation time of other
          links along the network path and the queueing delay in network
          equipment. The delay is increased when multiple hops are used
          (i.e. communications is relayed via a gateway) or if inter-satellite
          links are used. As satellites become more complex and include
          on-board processing of signals, additional delay can be added.</t>

          <t>Communications satellites can also be built to use a Low Earth
          Orbit (LEO) <xref target="Stu95"></xref> <xref
          target="Mon98"></xref>. The lower orbits require the use of
          constellations of satellites for constant coverage. In other words,
          as one satellite leaves the ground station's sight, another
          satellite appears on the horizon and the channel is switched to it.
          The propagation delay to a LEO orbit ranges from several
          milliseconds when communicating with a satellite directly overhead,
          to as much as 20 ms when the satellite is on the horizon. Some of
          these systems use inter-satellite links and have variable path delay
          depending on routing through the network.</t>

          <t>Another orbital position use a Medium Earth Orbit (MEO) <xref
          target="Mar78"></xref>. These orbits lie between LEO and GEO.</t>
        </list></t>

      <section title="Geosynchronous Earth Orbit (GEO)">
        <t>The characteristics of systems using Geosynchronous Earth Orbit
        (GEO) satellites differ from paths only using terrestrial links in
        their path characteristics: <list style="symbols">
            <t>A large propagation delay of at least 250ms one-way delay;</t>

            <t>Use of radio resource management (often using techniques
            similar to cellular mobile or DOCSIS cable networks, but differ
            to accommodate the satellite propagation delay);</t>

	    <t>Links can be highly asymmetric (in terms of capacity, one-way
	    delay and in their cost of operation, see <xref
	    target="referencescenarios"></xref> for example scenarios).</t>
          </list>As an example. GEO systems use the DVB-S2 specifications
        [EN 302 307-1], published by the European Telecommunications Standards
        Institute (ETSI), where the key concept is to ensure both a good usage
        of the satellite resource and a Quasi Error Free (QEF) link. These
        systems typically monitor the link quality in real-time, with the help
        of known symbol sequences, included along with regular packets, which
        enable an estimation of the current signal-to-noise ratio. This
        estimation is then feedback allowing the transmitting link to adapt
        its coding rate and modulation to the actual transmission
        conditions.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Low Earth Orbit (LEO)">
	<t>There is an important variability of LEO systems. Depending on the
	locations of the gateways on the ground, routing within the
	constellation may be necessary to bring to packets down to the ground.
	Depending on the routes currently available for an end user, high
	levels of jitter may occur (from 40ms to 140ms with the Iridium
	constellation). This may lead to out-of-order delivery of packets.</t>

        <t>XXX The authors solicit feedback and experience from users and
        operators of satellite systems in LEO orbits. XXX</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Medium Earth Orbit (MEO)">
        <t>MEO systems such as O3B combines advantages and drawbacks from both
        LEO and GEO systems.</t>

	<t>MEO systems can have a large coverage and with limited number of
	satellites required providing a broad service.  The usage of powerful
	satellites enables provision of high data rates.</t>

	<t>MEO systems have the drawback, from a transport protocol
	perspective, that the BDP can be very high due to the altitude of such
	constellations (8 063 km for O3B) and there may be delay variations
	when the satellite changes (every 45 minutes with O3B). The latter can
	be dealt with by means of double antennas terminals.</t>

        <t>XXX The authors solicit feedback and experience from users and
        operators of satellite systems in MEO orbits. XXX</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Hybrid Network Paths">
        <t>XXX The authors solicit feedback and experience from users and
        operators of satellite systems in hybrid network scenarios. XXX</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="s-characteristics"
             title="Satellite System Characteristics">
      <t>There is an inherent delay in the delivery of a packet over a
      satellite system due to the finite speed of light and the altitude of
      communications satellites.</t>

      <t>Satellite links are dominated by two fundamental characteristics, as
      described below:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
	  <t>Packet Loss: The strength of any radio signal falls in proportion
	  to the square of the distance traveled. For a satellite link the
	  square of the distance traveled is large and so the signal becomes
	  weak before reaching its destination. This results in a low
	  signal-to-noise ratio. Some frequencies are particularly susceptible
	  to atmospheric effects such as rain attenuation. For mobile
	  applications, satellite channels are especially susceptible to
	  multi-path distortion and shadowing (e.g., blockage by buildings).
	  Typical bit error ratios (BER) for a satellite link today are on the
	  order of 1 error per 10 million bits (1 x 10^-7) or less frequent.
	  Advanced error control coding (e.g., Reed Solomon or LDPC) can be
	  added to existing satellite services and is currently being used by
	  many services. Satellite performance approaching fiber will become
	  more common using advanced error control coding in new systems.
	  However, many legacy satellite systems will continue to exhibit
	  higher physical layer BER than newer satellite systems. TCP uses all
	  packet drops as signals of network congestion and reduces its window
	  size in an attempt to alleviate the congestion. In the absence of
	  knowledge about why a packet was dropped (congestion or corruption),
	  TCP must assume the drop was due to network congestion to avoid
	  congestion collapse <xref target="Jac88"></xref> <xref
	  target="FF98"></xref>. Therefore, packets dropped due to corruption
	  cause TCP to reduce the size of its sliding window, even though these
	  packet drops do not signal congestion in the network.</t>

          <t>Bandwidth: The radio spectrum is a limited natural resource,
          there is a restricted amount of bandwidth available to
          satellite systems which is typically controlled by licenses. This
          scarcity makes it difficult to trade bandwidth to solve other design
          problems. Satellite-based radio repeaters are known as transponders.
          Traditional C-band transponder bandwidth is typically 36 MHz to
          accommodate one color television channel (or 1200 voice channels).
          Ku-band transponders are typically around 50 MHz. Furthermore, one
          satellite may carry a few dozen transponders. Not only is bandwidth
          limited by nature, but the allocations for commercial communications
          are limited by international agreements so that this scarce resource
          can be used fairly by many different communications applications.
          Typical carrier frequencies for current, point- to-point,
          commercial, satellite services are 6 GHz (uplink) and 4 GHz
          (downlink), also known as C-band, and 14/12 GHz (Ku band). Services
          also utilise higher bands, including 30/20 GHz (Ka-band).

	  XXX  JB: I think we need add Ka-band details.
	  You cannot get 250 Mbps out of a C-band or Ku-band transponder.
	  Outbound Ka-band transponders range from 100 to 500 MHz.  Inbound
	  Ka-band transponders range from 50 to 250 MHz.XXX </t>

          <t>Link Design: It is common to consider the satellite network
          segment composed of a forward link and a return link. The forward
          link (also called "downlink") is the link from the ground station
          of the satellite to the user terminal. The return link (also called
          "uplink") is the link in the opposite direction. These two links
          can have different capacities and employ different technologies to
          carry the IP packets. On the forward link, the satellite gateway
          often manages all the available capacity, possibly with several
          carriers, to communicate with a set of remote terminals. A carrier
          is a single Time-Division-Multiplexing (TDM) channel that
          multiplexes packets addressed to specific terminals. There are
          trade-offs in terms of overall system efficiency and performance
          observed by a user. Most systems incur additional delay to ensure
          overall system performance.</t>

          <t>Shared Medium Access: In common with other radio media, satellite
          capacity can be assigned for use by a link for a period of time, for
          the duration of communication, for a per-packet or per burst of
          packets, or accessed using contention mechanisms. Packets sent over
          a shared radio channels need to be sent in frames that need to be
          allocated resources (bandwidth, power, time) for their transmission.
          This results in a range of characteristics that are very different
          to a permanently assigned medium (such as an Ethernet link using an
          optical fibre). On the return link, satellite resource is typically
          dynamically shared among the terminals. Two access methods can be
          distinguished: on-demand access or contention access. In the former,
          a terminal receives dedicated transmission resources (usually to
          send to the gateway). In the latter, some resources are reserved for
          contention access, where a set of terminals are allowed to compete
          to obtain transmission resource. Dedicated access, which is more
          common in currently deployed systems, can be through a Demand
          Assigned Multiple Access (DAMA) mechanism, while contention access
          techniques are usually based on Slotted Aloha (SA) and its numerous
          derivatives. More information on satellite links characteristics can
          be found in <xref target="RFC2488"></xref> <xref
          target="IJSCN17"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Satellite systems have several characteristics that differ from most
      terrestrial channels. These characteristics may degrade the performance
      of TCP. These characteristics include:</t>

      <section title="Impact of delay ">
        <t>Even for characteristics shared with terrestrial paths, the impact
        on a satellite link could be amplified by the path RTT. For example,
        paths using a satellite system can also exhibit a high loss-rate
        (e.g., a mobile user or a user behind a Wi-Fi link), where the
        additional delay can impact transport mechanisms.</t>

        <section title="Larger Bandwidth Delay Product">
          <t>Although capacity is often less than in many terrestrial systems,
          the bandwidth delay product (BDP) defines the amount of data that a
          protocol is permitted to have "in flight" at any one time to fully
          utilize the available capacity. In flight means data that is transmitted,
          but not yet acknowledged.</t>

          <t>The delay used in this equation is the path RTT and the bandwidth
          is the capacity of the bottleneck link along the network path.
          Because the delay in some satellite environments is higher,
          protocols need to keep a larger number of packets in flight.</t>

          <t>This also impacts the size of window/credit needed to avoid flow
          control mechanisms throttling the sender rate.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Variable Link Delay">
          <t>In some satellite environments, such as some Low Earth Orbit
          (LEO) constellations, the propagation delay to and from the
          satellite varies over time.</t>

          <t>Even when the propagation delay varies only very slightly, the
          effects of medium access methods can result in significant variation
          in the link delay. Whether or not this will have an impact on
          performance of a well-designed transport is currently an open
          question.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Impact of delay on protocol feedback">
          <t>The link delay of some satellite systems may require more time
          for a transport sender to determine whether or not a packet has been
          successfully received at the final destination. This delay impacts
          interactive applications as well as loss recovery, congestion
          control, flow control, and other algorithms (see <xref
          target="s-transport"></xref>).</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Intermittent connectivity">
        <t>In some non-GEO satellite orbit configurations, from time to time
        Internet connections need to be transferred from one satellite to
        another or from one ground station to another. This hand-off might
        cause excessive packet loss or reordering if not properly
        performed.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="s-below-transport"
             title="On-Path Mitigations">
      <t>This section describes mitigations that operate on the path, rather
      than with the transport endpoints.</t>

      <section title="Link-Level Forward Error Correction and ARQ">
        <t>XXX Common, but includes adaptive ModCod and sometimes ARQ - which
        can reduce the loss at the expense of decreasing the available
        capacity. XXX</t>
      </section>

      <section title="PMTU Discovery">
        <t>XXX Packet Size can impact performance and mitigations (such as
        PEP/Application Proxy) can interact with end-to-end PMTUD XXX</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Quality of Service (QoS)">
        <t>Links where packets are sent over radio channels exhibit various
        trade-offs in the way the signal is sent on the communications channel.
        These trade-offs are not necessarily the same for all packets, and
        network traffic flows can be optimised by mapping these onto different
        types of lower layer treatment (packet queues, resource management
        requests, resource usage, and adaption to the channel using FEC, ARQ,
        etc). Many systems differentiate classes of traffic to mange these QoS
        trade-offs.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Split-TCP PEP">
        <t>High BDP networks commonly break the TCP end-to-end paradigm to
        adapt the transport protocol. Splitting a TCP connection allows
        adaptation for a specific use-case and to address the issues discussed
        in Section 2. Satellite communications commonly deploy Performance
        Enhancing Proxy (PEP) for compression, caching and TCP acceleration
        services <xref target="RFC3135"> </xref> . Their deployment can result
        in significant performance improvement (e.g., a 50% page load time
        reduction in a SATCOM use-case <xref target="ICCRG100"> </xref> .</t>

        <t><xref target="NCT13"> </xref> and <xref target="RFC3135"> </xref>
        describe the main functions of a SATCOM TCP split solution. For
        traffic originated at a gateway to an endpoint connected via a
        satellite terminal, the TCP split proxy intercepts TCP SYN packets,
        acting on behalf of the endpoint and adapts the sending rate to the
        SATCOM scenario. The split solution can specifically tune TCP
        parameters to the satellite link (latency, available capacity).</t>

        <t>When a proxy is used on each side of the satellite link, the
        transport protocol can be replaced by a protocol other than TCP,
        optimized for the satellite link. This can be tuned using a priori
        information about the satellite system and/or by measuring the
        properties of the network segment that includes the satellite
        system.</t>

        <t>Split connections can also recover from packet loss that is local
        to the part of the connection on which the packet losses occur. This
        eliminates the need for end-to-end recovery of lost packets.</t>

        <t>One important advantage of a TCP split solution is that it does not
        require any end-to-end modification and is independent of both the
        client and server sides. </t>

	<t> Split-TCP comes with a significant drawback: TCP splitters are
	often unable to track end-to-end improvements in protocol mechanisms
	(e.g., RACK, ECN, TCP Fast Open) or new protocols that share a wire
	format with TCP (MPTCP <xref target="RFC6824"></xref>). The set of
	methods configured in a split proxy usually continue to be used, until
	the split solution is finally updated. This can delay/negate the
	benefit of any end-to-end improvements, contributing to ossification of
	the transport system.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Application Proxies">
        <t>Authenticated proxies:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Split some functions, so the proxy needs to agree on the
            formats/semantics of the protocol info that is changed</t>

            <t>Need a trust relationship - need to be authenticated, and
            understand what is modified</t>

            <t>Proxy needs to be on-path, which places constraints on the
            routing via the box</t>

            <t>Need to discover the device, which might vary by user - by
            service - etc.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="s-transport"
             title="Generic Transport Protocol Mechanisms">
      <t>This section outlines transport protocol mechanisms that may be
      necessary to tune or optimize in satellite or hybrid
      satellite/terrestrial networks to better utilize the available capacity
      of the link. These mechanisms may also be needed to fully utilize fast
      terrestrial channels. Furthermore, these mechanisms do not fundamentally
      hurt performance in a shared terrestrial network. Each of the following
      sections outlines one mechanism and why that mechanism may be
      needed.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Transport initialization: the connection handshake (in TCP the
          3-way exchange) takes a longer time to complete, delaying the time
          to send data (several transport protocol exchanges may be needed,
          such as TLS);</t>

          <t>Size of congestion window required: to fully exploit the
          bottleneck capacity, a high BDP requires a larger number of
          in-flight packets;</t>

          <t>Size of receiver (flow control) window required: to fully exploit
          the bottleneck capacity, a high BDP requires a larger number of
          in-flight packets;</t>

          <t>Reliability: transport layer loss detection and repair can incur
          a single or multiple RTTs (the performance of end-to-end
          retransmission is also impacted when using a high RTT path);</t>

          <t>Getting up to speed: many congestion control methods employ an
          exponential increase in the sending rate during slow start (for path
          capacity probing), a high RTT will increase the time to reach the
          maximum possible rate;</t>

	  <t>Asymmetry: when the links are asymmetric the return path may
	  modify the rate and/timing of transport acknowledgment traffic,
	  potentially changing behaviour (e.g., limiting the forward sending
	  rate).</t>
        </list></t>

      <section title="Transport Initialization">
        <t>Many transport protocols now deploy 0-RTT mechanisms [REF] to
        reduce the number of RTTs required to establish a connection. QUIC has
        an advantage that the TLS and TCP negotiations can be completed during
        the transport connection handshake. This can reduce the time to
        transmit the first data.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Getting up to Speed">
        <t>Results of <xref target="IJSCN19"> </xref> illustrate that it
        can still take many RTTs for a CC to increase the sending rate to fill
        the bottleneck capacity. The delay in getting up to speed can dominate
        performance for a path with a large RTT, and requires the congestion
        and flow controls to accommodate the impact of path delay.</t>

        <t>One relevant solution is tuning of the initial window described in
        <xref target="I-D.irtf-iccrg-sallantin-initial-spreading"> </xref> ,
        which has been shown to improve performance both for high BDP and more
        common BDP <xref target="CONEXT15"> </xref> <xref target="ICC16">
        </xref> . Such a solution requires using sender pacing to avoid
        generating bursts of packets in a network.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Sizing of Maxium Congestion Window">
        <t>Size of windows required: to fully exploit the bottleneck capacity,
        a high BDP requires a larger number of in-flight packets.</t>

        <t>The number of in-flight packets required to fill a bottleneck
        capacity, is dependent on the BDP. Default values of maximum windows
        may not be suitable for a SATCOM context.</t>

        <t>Such as presented in <xref target="PANRG105"> </xref> , only
        increasing the initial congestion window is not the only way that can
        improve QUIC performance in a SATCOM context: increasing maximum
        congestion windows can also result in much better performance. Other
        protocol mechanisms also need to be considered, such as flow control
        at the stream level in QUIC.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reliability (Loss Recovery/Repair)">
        <t>The time for end systems to perform packet loss detection and
        recovery/repair is a function of the path RTT.</t>

        <t>The RTT also determines the time needed by a server to react to a
        congestion event. Both can impact the user experience. For example,
        when a user uses a Wi-Fi link to access the Internet via SATCOM
        terminal.</t>

        <t>A solution could be to opportunistically retransmit packets even if they have not been detected as lost but the congestion control allows to transmit more packets.</t>

        <section title="Packet Level Forward Error Correction">
	  <t>XXX Packet level FEC can mitigate loss/re-ordering, with a
		  trade-off in capacity. XXX</t>

        <t>End-to-end packet Forward Error Correction offers an alternative to
        retransmission with different trade offs in terms of utilised capacity
		and repair capability.</t>

        <t>The benefits of introducing FEC need to weighed against the
        additional overhead introduced by end-to-end FEC and the opportunity
        to use link-local ARQ and/or link-adaptive FEC. A transport
        connections can suffer link-related losses from a particular link
        (e.g., Wi-Fi), but also congestion loss (e.g. router buffer overflow
	in a satellite operator ground segment or along an Internet path).</t>
        <!-- Mechanisms have been proposed in <xref
        target="I-D.ferrieux-hamchaoui-quic-lossbits"> </xref> , to identify
	congestion losses in the ground segment.</t> -->

        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Flow Control">
        <t>Flow Control mechanisms allow the receiver to control the amount of
        data a sender can have in flight at any time. Flow Control allows the
        receiver to allocate the smallest buffer sizes possible improving
        memory usage on receipt.</t>

        <t>The sizing of initial receive buffers requires a balance between
        keeping receive memory allocation small while allowing the send window
        to grow quickly to help ensure high utilization. The size of receive
        windows and their growth can govern the performance of the protocol if
        updates are not timely. </t>

        <t>Many TCP implementations deploy Auto-scaling mechanisms to increase
        the size of the largest receive window over time. If these increases
        are not timely then sender traffic can stall while waiting to be
        notified of an increase in receive window size. XXX QUIC? XXX</t>

        <t>Multi-streaming Protocols such as QUIC implement Flow Control using
        credit-based mechanisms that allow the receiver to prioritise which
        stream is able to send and when. Credit-based systems, when flow
        credit allocations are not timely, can stall sending when credit
        is exhausted.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="ACK Traffic Reduction">
        <t>When the links are asymmetric, for various reasons, the return
        path may modify the rate and/timing of transport acknowledgment
        traffic, potentially changing behaviour (e.g., limiting the forward
        sending rate).</t>

        <t>Asymmetry in capacity (or in the way capacity is granted to a flow)
        can lead to cases where the transmission in one direction of
        communication is restricted by the transmission of the acknowledgment
        traffic flowing in the opposite direction. A network segment could
        present limitations in the volume of acknowledgment traffic (e.g.,
        limited available return path capacity) or in the number of
        acknowledgment packets (e.g., when a radio-resource management system
        has to track channel usage), or both.</t>

        <t>TCP Performance Implications of Network Path Asymmetry <xref
        target="RFC3449"> </xref> describes a range of mechanisms that have
        been used to mitigate the impact of path asymmetry, primarily
        targeting operation of TCP.</t>

        <t>Many mitigations have been deployed in satellite systems, often as
        a mechanism within a PEP. Despite their benefits over paths with high
        asymmetry, most mechanisms rely on being able to inspect and/or modify
        the transport layer header information of TCP ACK packets. This is not
        possible when the transport layer information is encrypted (e.g.,
        using an IP VPN).</t>

        <t>One simple mitigation is for the remote endpoint to send compound
        acknowledgments less frequently. A rate of one ACK for every RTT/4 can
        significantly reduce this traffic. The QUIC transport specification
        may evolve to allow the ACK Ratio to be adjusted.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Multi-Path">
        <t>XXX This includes between different satellite systems and between
        satellite and terrestrial paths XXX</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="s-proto-spec" title="Protocol Specific Mechanisms">
      <section title="TCP Protocol Mechanisms">
        <section title="Transport Initialization"></section>

        <section title="Getting Up To Speed">
          <t>One relevant solution is tuning of the initial window described
          in <xref target="I-D.irtf-iccrg-sallantin-initial-spreading">
          </xref><xref target="RFC6928"></xref>, which has been shown to
          improve performance both for high BDP and more common BDP <xref
          target="CONEXT15"> </xref> <xref target="ICC16"> </xref>. This
          requires sender pacing to avoid generating bursts of packets to the
          network.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Size of Windows"></section>

        <section title="Reliability"></section>

        <section title="ACK Reduction">
          <t>Mechanisms are being proposed in TCPM for TCP [REF].</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="QUIC Protocol Mechanisms">
        <section title="Transport initialization">
          <t>QUIC has an advantage that the TLS and transport protocol negotiations
          can be completed during the transport connection handshake. This can
          reduce the time to transmit the first data. Moreover, using 0-RTT may
          further reduce the connection time for users reconnecting to a
          server.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Getting up to Speed">
          <t>Getting up to speed may be easier with the usage of the 0-RTT-BDP
          extension proposed in <xref
          target="I-D.kuhn-quic-0rtt-bdp"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Size of Windows "></section>

        <section title="Reliability">
		<!-- <t>Mechanisms have been proposed in <xref
          target="I-D.ferrieux-hamchaoui-quic-lossbits"> </xref> , to identify
		congestion losses in the ground segment.</t> -->
        </section>

        <section title="Asymmetry">
          <t>The QUIC transport specification may evolve to allow the ACK
          Ratio to be adjusted.</t>

          <t>Default could be adapted following <xref
          target="I-D.fairhurst-quic-ack-scaling"></xref> or using extensions
          to tune acknowledgement strategies <xref
          target="I-D.iyengar-quic-delayed-ack"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Packet Level Forward Error Correction">
          <t>Network coding as proposed in <xref
          target="I-D.swett-nwcrg-coding-for-quic"> </xref> and <xref
          target="I-D.roca-nwcrg-rlc-fec-scheme-for-quic"> </xref> could help
          QUIC recover from link or congestion loss.</t>

          <t>Another approach could utilise QUIC tunnels such as proposed in the MASQUE WG 
          to apply packet FEC to all or
          a part of the end-to-end path or enable local retransmissions.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Split Congestion Control ">
          <t>Splitting the congestion control requires the deployment of
          application proxies.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec:discussion" title="Discussion">
      <t>Many of the issues identified for high BDP paths already exist when
      using an encrypted transport service over a path that employs encryption
      at the IP layer. This includes endpoints that utilise IPsec at the
      network layer, or use VPN technology over a satellite network segment.
      Users are unable to benefit from enhancement within the satellite
      network segment, and often the user is unaware of the presence of the
      satellite link on their path, except through observing the impact it has
      on the performance they experience.</t>

      <t>One solution would be to provide PEP functions at the termination of
      the security association (e.g., in a VPN client). Another solution could
      be to fall-back to using TCP (possibly with TLS or similar methods being
      used on the transport payload). A different solution could be to deploy
      and maintain a bespoke protocol tailored to high BDP environments. In
      the future, we anticipate that fall-back to TCP will become less
      desirable, and methods that rely upon bespoke configurations or
      protocols will be unattractive. In parallel, new methods such as QUIC
      will become widely deployed. The opportunity therefore exists to ensure
      that the new generation of protocols offer acceptable performance over
      high BDP paths without requiring operating tuning or specific updates by
      users.</t>

      <section title="Mitigation Summary">
        <t>XXX A Table will be inserted here XXX</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec:acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Mark Allman, Daniel R. Glover and
      Luis A. Sanchez the authors of RFC2488 from which the format and
      descriptions of satellite systems in this document have taken
      inspiration.</t>

      <t>The authors would like to thank Christian Huitema, Igor Lubashev,
      Alexandre Ferrieux, Francois Michel, Emmanuel Lochin, github user
      sedrubal and the participants of the IETF106 side-meeting on QUIC for
      high BDP for their useful feedback.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec:ecurity" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not propose changes to the security functions
      provided by the QUIC protocol. QUIC uses TLS encryption to protect the
      transport header and its payload. Security is considered in the
      "Security Considerations" of cited IETF documents.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
	1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
	2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
	(for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")
	Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
	If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
	directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
	with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
	filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <!-- <references title="Normative References">
		&RFC2119;
	</references> -->

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.fairhurst-quic-ack-scaling.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.iyengar-quic-delayed-ack.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.kuhn-quic-0rtt-bdp.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2488.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2760.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3135.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3449.xml"?>

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6349.xml"?> -->

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6534.xml"?> -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6824.xml"?>
	    
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6928.xml"?>
	    
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9000.xml"?>
	    
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8975.xml"?>

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7928.xml"?> -->

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8446.xml"?> -->

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.swett-nwcrg-coding-for-quic.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.roca-nwcrg-rlc-fec-scheme-for-quic.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.irtf-panrg-path-properties.xml">

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.schinazi-masque.xml"?> -->

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ferrieux-hamchaoui-quic-lossbits.xml"?> -->

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-quic-tls.xml"?> -->

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-quic-transport.xml"?> -->

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-quic-recovery.xml"?> -->

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tls-ticketrequests.xml"?> -->

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.irtf-iccrg-sallantin-initial-spreading.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="Sta94">
        <front>
          <title>Data and Computer Communications</title>

          <author initials="W" surname="Stallings"></author>

          <date year="1994" />
        </front>

	<seriesInfo name="MacMillian" value="4th edition" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Mar78">
        <front>
          <title>Communications Satellite Systems</title>

          <author initials="J" surname="Martin"></author>

          <date year="1978" />
        </front>

	<seriesInfo name="Prentice Hall" value="78" />
      </reference>

   
      <reference anchor="Stu95">
        <front>
          <title>Architecture of the TELEDESIC Satellite System</title>

          <author initials="M.A." surname="Sturza"></author>

          <date year="1995" />
        </front>

	<seriesInfo name="International Mobile Satellite Conference" value="95" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Mon98">
        <front>
          <title>TELEDESIC: Enabling The Global Community Interaccess</title>

          <author initials="M.J." surname="Montpetit"></author>

          <date year="1998" />
        </front>

	<seriesInfo name="International Wireless Symposium" value="98" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Jac88">
        <front>
          <title>Congestion Avoidance and Control</title>

          <author initials="V" surname="Jacobson"></author>

          <date year="1988" />
        </front>

	<seriesInfo name="ACM SIGCOMM" value="88" />
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="FF98">
        <front>
          <title>Promoting the Use of End-to-End Congestion Control in the Internet</title>

          <author initials="S" surname="Floyd"></author>

          <author initials="K" surname="Fall"></author>

          <date year="1999" />
        </front>

	<seriesInfo name="IEEE Transactions on Networking" value="10.1109/90.79302" />
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="PANRG105">
        <front>
          <title>QUIC Over In-sequence Paths with Different
          Characteristics</title>

          <author initials="N" surname="Kuhn"></author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Stephan"></author>

          <author initials="J" surname="Border"></author>

          <author initials="G" surname="Fairhurst"></author>

          <date year="2019" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="IRTF PANRG" value="105" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ICCRG100">
        <front>
          <title>MPTCP and BBR performance over Internet satellite
          paths</title>

          <author initials="N" surname="Kuhn"></author>

          <date year="2017" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="IETF ICCRG" value="100" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IJSCN17">
        <front>
          <title>Software-defined satellite cloud RAN</title>

          <author initials="T" surname="Ahmed"></author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Dubois"></author>

          <author initials="JB" surname="Dupe"></author>

          <author initials="R" surname="Ferrus"></author>

          <author initials="P" surname="Gelard"></author>

          <author initials="N" surname="Kuhn"></author>

          <date year="2017" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="International Journal of Satellite Communications and Networking"
                    value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IJSCN19">
        <front>
          <title>Google QUIC performance over a public SATCOM access</title>

          <author initials="L" surname="Thomas"></author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Dubois"></author>

          <author initials="N" surname="Kuhn"></author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Lochin"></author>

          <date year="2019" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="International Journal of Satellite Communications and Networking"
                    value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CONEXT15">
        <front>
          <title>Halfback: Running Short Flows Quickly and Safely</title>

          <author initials="Q" surname="Li"></author>

          <author initials="M" surname="Dong"></author>

          <author initials="P B" surname="Godfrey"></author>

          <date year="2015" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ACM CoNEXT" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="NCT13">
        <front>
          <title>A new survey on improving TCP performances over geostationary
          satellite link</title>

          <author initials="A" surname="Pirovano"></author>

          <author initials="F" surname="Garcia"></author>

          <date year="2013" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Network and Communication Technologies" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ICC16">
        <front>
          <title>Reducing web latency through TCP IW: Be smart</title>

          <author initials="R" surname="Sallantin"></author>

          <author initials="C" surname="Baudoin"></author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Chaput"></author>

          <author initials="F" surname="Arnal"></author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Dubois"></author>

          <author initials="A-L" surname="Beylot"></author>

          <date year="2016" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="IEEE ICC" value="" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="referencescenarios" title="Example Network Profiles">
      <t>This proposes sampler profiles and a set of regression tests to
      evaluate transport protocols over SATCOM links and discusses how to
      ensure acceptable protocol performance.</t>

      <t>XXX These test profiles currently focus on the measuring performance and
      testing for regressions in the QUIC protocol. The authors solicit input
      to adapt these tests to apply to more transport protocols. XXX</t>

      <section title="LEO"></section>

      <section title="MEO"></section>

      <section title="GEO">
        <t>This section proposes a set of regression tests for QUIC that
        consider high BDP scenarios. We define by:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Download path: from Internet to the client endpoint;</t>

            <t>Upload path: from the client endpoint to a server (e.g., in the
            Internet).</t>
          </list></t>

        <section title="Small public satellite broadband access">
          <t>The tested scenario has the following path characteristics:<list
              style="symbols">
              <t>Satellite downlink path: 10 Mbps</t>

              <t>Satellite uplink path: 2 Mbps</t>

              <t>No emulated packet loss</t>

              <t>RTT: 650 ms</t>

              <t>Buffer size : BDP</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>During the transmission of 100 MB on both download and upload
          paths, the test should report the upload and download time of 2 MB,
          10 MB and 100 MB.</t>

          <t>Initial thoughts of the performance objectives for QUIC are the
          following:<list style="symbols">
              <t>3 s for downloading 2 MB</t>

              <t>10 s for downloading 10 MB</t>

              <t>85 s for downloading 100 MB</t>

              <t>10 s for uploading 2 MB</t>

              <t>50 s for uploading 10 MB</t>

              <t>420 s for uploading 100 MB</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Medium public satellite broadband access">
          <t>The tested scenario has the following path characteristics:<list
              style="symbols">
              <t>Satellite downlink path: 50 Mbps</t>

              <t>Satellite uplink path: 10 Mbps</t>

              <t>No emulated packet loss</t>

              <t>RTT: 650 ms</t>

              <t>Buffer size : BDP</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>During the transmission of 100 MB on the download path, the test
          should report the download time for 2 MB, 10 MB and 100 MB. Then, to
          assess the performance of QUIC with the 0-RTT extension and its
          variants, after 10 seconds, repeat the transmission of 100 MB on the
          download path where the download time for 2 MB, 10 MB and 100 MB is
          recorded.</t>

          <t>Initial thoughts of the performance objectives for QUIC are the
          following:<list style="symbols">
              <t>3 s for the first downloading 2 MB</t>

              <t>5 s for the first downloading 10 MB</t>

              <t>20 s for the first downloading 100 MB</t>

              <t>TBD s for the second downloading 2 MB</t>

              <t>TBD s for the second downloading 10 MB</t>

              <t>TBD s for the second downloading 100 MB</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Congested medium public satellite broadband access">
          <t>There are cases where the uplink path is congested or where the
          capacity of the uplink path is not guaranteed.</t>

          <t>The tested scenario has the following path characteristics:<list
              style="symbols">
              <t>Satellite downlink path: 50 Mbps</t>

              <t>Satellite uplink path: 0.5 Mbps</t>

              <t>No emulated packet loss</t>

              <t>RTT: 650 ms</t>

              <t>Buffer size : BDP</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>During the transmission of 100 MB on the download path, the test
          should report the download time for 2 MB, 10 MB and 100 MB.</t>

          <t>Initial thoughts of the performance objectives for QUIC are the
          following:<list style="symbols">
              <t>3 s for downloading 2 MB</t>

              <t>5 s for downloading 10 MB</t>

              <t>20 s for downloading 100 MB</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Variable medium public satellite broadband access">
          <t>There are cases where the downlink path is congested or where,
          due to link layer adaptations to rain fading, the capacity of the
          downlink path is variable.</t>

          <t>The tested scenario has the following path characteristics:<list
              style="symbols">
              <t>Satellite downlink path: 50 Mbps - wait 5s - 10 Mbps</t>

              <t>Satellite uplink path: 10 Mbps</t>

              <t>No emulated packet loss</t>

              <t>RTT: 650 ms</t>

              <t>Buffer size : BDP</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>During the transmission of 100 MB on the download path, the test
          should report the download time for 2 MB, 10 MB and 100 MB.</t>

          <t>Initial thoughts of the performance objectives for QUIC are the
          following:<list style="symbols">
              <t>TBD s for downloading 2 MB</t>

              <t>TBD s for downloading 10 MB</t>

              <t>TBD s for downloading 100 MB</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Loss-free large public satellite broadband access">
          <t>The tested scenario has the following path characteristics:<list
              style="symbols">
              <t>Satellite downlink path: 250 Mbps</t>

              <t>Satellite uplink path: 6 Mbps</t>

              <t>No emulated packet loss</t>

              <t>RTT: 650 ms</t>

              <t>Buffer size : BDP</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>During the transmission of 100 MB on the download path, the test
          should report the download time for 2 MB, 10 MB and 100 MB. Then, to
          assess the performance of QUIC with the 0-RTT extension and its
          variants, after 10 seconds, repeat the transmission of 100 MB on the
          download path where the download time for 2 MB, 10 MB and 100 MB is
          recorded.</t>

          <t>Initial thoughts of the performance objectives for QUIC are the
          following:<list style="symbols">
              <t>3 s for the first downloading 2 MB</t>

              <t>5 s for the first downloading 10 MB</t>

              <t>8 s for the first downloading 100 MB</t>

              <t>TBD s for the second downloading 2 MB</t>

              <t>TBD s for the second downloading 10 MB</t>

              <t>TBD s for the second downloading 100 MB</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Lossy large public satellite broadband access">
          <t>The tested scenario has the following path characteristics:<list
              style="symbols">
              <t>Satellite downlink path: 250 Mbps</t>

              <t>Satellite uplink path: 6 Mbps</t>

              <t>Emulated packet loss on both downlink and uplink paths:<list
                  style="symbols">
                  <t>Uniform random transmission link losses: 1%</t>

                  <!-- <t>Bursty losses, including transmission and congestion losses: P(g|g)= 0.982, P(g|b)= 0.645, P(b|b)= 0.355, P(b|g)= 0.018 (see <xref target="RFC6534"></xref> for more details)</t> -->
                </list></t>

              <t>RTT: 650 ms</t>

              <t>Buffer size : BDP</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>During the transmission of 100 MB on the download path, the test
          should report the download time for 2 MB, 10 MB and 100 MB.</t>

          <t>Initial thoughts of the performance objectives for QUIC are the
          following:<list style="symbols">
              <t>3 s for downloading 2 MB (uniform transmission link
              losses)</t>

              <t>6 s for downloading 10 MB (uniform transmission link
              losses)</t>

              <t>10 s for downloading 100 MB (uniform transmission link
              losses)</t>

              <!-- <t>TBD s for downloading 2 MB (bursty transmission and congestion losses)</t>
			<t>TBD s for downloading 10 MB (bursty transmission and congestion losses)</t>
			<t>TBD s for downloading 100 MB (bursty transmission and congestion losses)</t> -->
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Revision Notes">
      <t>Note to RFC-Editor: please remove this entire section prior to
      publication.</t>

      <t>Individual draft -00:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Comments and corrections are welcome directly to the authors or
          via the
          https://github.com/uoaerg/draft-jones-transport-for-satellite github
          repo in the form of pull requests and issues.</t>
        </list></t>
      <t>Individual draft -01:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Explained Terms Forward and return link</t>
	  <t>Rearranged text to help the document read better</t>
	  <t>Fix typos and inaccuracies</t>
	  <t>Added a mention of MPTCP</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
